Okay, so we are on דף כז *Daf Kaf Zayin* in תמיד
Tamid *Tamid* where in the middle of the first פרק *perek* lag
baomer and we pick up on three lines from the top תנן
התם *T’nan Hatam*. Now I did want to mention by the way
a couple of things that came up yesterday I researched a little.
First of all the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had made it sound like
there was only one כהן Kohen *Kohen* per station. The רמב״ם *Rambam*
when he discusses the watchings says that there is an עדה של
כהנים kohanim *edah shel Kohanim* at each station, a community, a group,
a collective, it’s not exactly clear what he means. A number of
אחרונים *Acharonim* think he means ten because the idea of עדה *edah*
is where we learn the idea of a מנין *minyan* from. But
anyway what is important is that the רמב״ם *Rambam* says that it’s
not just one כהן kohen, *Kohen* at each station, it is a
group of כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim*. The also the question was raised by
the way yesterday about
non-Jews coming into the מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash* space and I was correct.
Non-Jews are not allowed in the עזרת נשים ezrat nashim. *Ezrat Nashim*.
They are kept outside of the חיל *cheil*. The חיל *cheil* is
this outer wall here around. They are not, they are not, yeah.
So also a טמא tamei. מת *tamei meis* although biblically a טמא
מת *tamei meis* is allowed on הר הבית Har Habayit, *Har Habayit*
and technically biblically עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim. *Ezrat Nashim* is הר הבית
Har Habayit, *Har Habayit* but nevertheless they gave an additional קדושה kedushah
*kedushah* to עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim, *Ezrat Nashim* and they said טמא
מת *tamei meis* was not allowed either. So that is the extra
rabbinic status that טמא מת *tamei meis*. בעל קרי Ba'al Keri, *Ba’al
keri* we’re going to see in today’s גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. בעל קרי
ba'al keri *Ba’al keri* is אסור assur. *assur* on הר הבית Har
Habayit. *Har Habayit*.
אסור assur *Assur*.
But a טבול יום tvul yom. *tevul yom* can go... a טבול
יום tvul yom *tevul yom* is also אסור assur *assur*.
So let’s go over here.
No, he had to he left completely. The question is how come
they let him wait till the morning? We had that discussion. When
non-Jews brought קרבנות *korbanos* what did they?
They would send them.
They would not personally be present. At least according to the way
the you know according to the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* and the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* that’s what they understand. In practice I don’t know who
knows. But anyway but according to that they would send them. Okay,
now let’s let’s keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. תנן התם *T’nan
Hatam*. Third line down on כז עמוד א aleph *Kaf Zayin Amud
Alef*. בשלושה מקומות *Bishlosha mekomos*. I had mentioned this when we first
read the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* that there’s a parallel of our משנה
Mishnah *Mishnah* at the beginning of מידות Middot. *Middot* but there it
talks about not just the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* but also the לויים
Levi'im *Levi’im*. So here’s what the first משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* in מידות
*Middot* says. בשלושה מקומות הכהנים שומרים בבית המקדש *Bishlosha mekomos haKohanim shomrim
b’Veis HaMikdash*. So it starts just like our first משנה Mishna. *Mishnah*.
Three places the כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim* guard in the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash*. בבית אבטינס ובבית הניצוץ ובבית המוקד *B’Veis Avtinas u’v’Veis
HaNitzotz u’v’Veis HaMoked*. Those three chambers that were that were in the
עזרה azarah, *azarah* that were sort of off in the walls of
the עזרה azarah, *azarah*. והלויים בעשרים ואחד מקום *VehaLevi’im b’esrim v’achad makom*.
And the לויים Levi'im *Levi’im* in twenty-one places. חמשה על חמשה שערי
הר הבית Har Habayit, *Chamisha al chamisha sha’arei Har Habayit*. Five on
the five walls of הר הבית Har Habayit, *Har Habayit*. Now you
realize well the one well I should say five gates. Okay that
did not... I thought that in some of these pictures although I
forgot to bring one it shows you not only this which is
the מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash* but this in reference to the walls around
the הר הבית Har Habayit *Har Habayit*. Right, I mean as you
know for example the כותל *Kotel* is a wall of the הר
הבית Har Habayit *Har Habayit*. It’s not a wall of the מקדש
Mikdash *Mikdash*. המקדש *HaMikdash* is up on the top of the Temple
Mount. The כותל *Kotel* is around at the bottom. So they were
the walls around at the bottom of the הר הבית Har Habayit
*Har Habayit*. And the לויים Levi'im *Levi’im* would be there. There would
be five gates that would enter in, right? You know that when
you go to the excavations, right, particularly on which wall is it,
the southern wall is it, you know that they have all of
those gates that you can see, you know where
they would be the exactly.
So those are the gates of הר הבית Har Habayit. *Har Habayit*.
Exactly, exactly. So those are the gates of הר הבית Har Habayit.
*Har Habayit*. Okay and there would be the לויים Levi'im *Levi’im* would
be five groups of לויים Levi'im *Levi’im* would watch there. Arba or
five לויים Levi'im *Levi’im* or five groups of לויים Leviim *Levi’im*. ארבע
arba על ארבע arba פינותיו *Arba al arba pinosav*. And four on
the four corners. Every wall you know if it’s four walls then
there are corners so each so there’s a group or a one
or a group of לויים Levi'im *Levi’im* at each corner doing a
watch. Now it’s actually quite interesting if you look at the מפרש
mefaresh *Meforesh* here and it says פינות *pinos* you see it’s like
about the first word of the line about ten lines down. He
says angles. You see that? אלף נון גימל למד צדיק *Aleph nun
gimmel lamed tzadik*. It’s almost like English. Angle. Okay so five anyway
so you would have five at the at the walls of the
הר הבית Har Habayit, *Har Habayit* you’d have five watches at the
five gates, four at the four corners. Now מבפנים *mibifnim*. All of
this it sound it could just be referring to the corners but
but anyway it seems like it’s all of this. All of those
watches would be on the inside of the walls, not on the
outside. Which is funny, right? You would think if you want a
sense of guards walking around and protecting particularly if it’s like the
corners, the gate, you could watch from the inside of a gate
or the outside of a gate. You know but anyway here it
says that that would all be from the inside of the wall.
Now that’s so now we have nine. חמשה על חמשה שערי עזרה
azarah *Chamisha al chamisha sha’arei azarah*. Five on the five gates of
the עזרה azarah *azarah*. Okay we’re going to ask if there’s really
five because we there’s other משניות *Mishnayot* that say seven. But anyway
that means the gates leaving in leading into those chambers that we’ve
been discussing. ארבע על *Arba al*... ארבע על ארבע פינותיה *Arba al
arba pinoteha* and four on the four corners of the עזרה azarah,
*Azara*. Now this is מבחוץ mibachutz, *mibachutz* on the outside. Okay so
that would be another nine on the both five four, five gates
four corners but of the עזרה azarah. *Azara* not of the not
of the הר הבית Har Ha-Bayis *Har HaBayis* and this is on
the outside. So we're up to eighteen. אחד בלשכת הקרבן ואחד בלשכת
הפרוכת ואחד אחורי בית הכפורת *Echad beLishkat HaKorban ve'echad beLishkat HaParochat ve'echad
achorei Beis HaKapporet*. Now one in the לשכת הקרבן *Lishkat HaKorban*. Where
is לשכת הקרבן *Lishkat HaKorban*? So when it says the five gates
of the עזרה azarah, *Azara* right so these are the chambers of
the עזרה Azara, *Azara* and each one had a gate. Okay of
course there there are seven in this picture and we said five
we'll talk about that. But in addition to those five gates this
the בית המוקד Beit HaMoked, *Beis HaMoked* which has been our focus
right which is where the כהנים kohanim, *Kohanim* slept right I'm sorry
maybe I'll use this
picture it's one I've been using
it's a little bit bigger. Okay this which is the בית *Beis*
so these are the places where you had gates right you had
these chambers and you had gates. This is the בית המוקד *Beis
HaMoked*. One of these on the inside here of the עזרה Azara,
*Azara* was called the לשכת הקרבן *Lishkat HaKorban*, the chamber of the
קרבן *korban* which was a chamber inside this larger this very large
room. So that was one of them. One in the בית הפרוכת
*Beis HaParochat*, not quite clear exactly where that was, and one behind
אחורי *achorei* and the other was where'd it say ואחד אחורי בית
הכפורת *ve'echad achorei Beis HaKapporet*. I'm sorry one in the לשכת הפרוכת
*Lishkat HaParochat* and the other is behind the בית הפרוכת *Beis HaParochat*.
This is the behind the בית הפרוכת *Beis HaParochat*. It is the
behind the קודש קדשים *Kodesh Kodashim*.
Wait there's no gate there though is there?
No presumably not.
See over here it says actually I'm just looking at this thing
I have. Here it says one שער שיר *Sha'ar Shir*, two שער
הנשים Sha'ar ha-Nashim. *Sha'ar HaNashim*, three שער *Sha'ar*...
What's your point that there are not five?
They're like more than seven.
I know. Well let's read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay fine let's
read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay anyway so there you would have
so you would have five and four around the gate and the
and the corners and then three other locations of which one is
behind the קודש קדשים *Kodesh Kodashim*, one is in the בית המוקד
*Beis HaMoked* and the other we don't know where it is.
Oh wait this shows the הר הבית Har Habayis *Har HaBayis* gates.
Okay. All right so let's pick up in the inside.
All right. I see it. It was like one over here, one
over here, two over there.
All right. Moving up. So now so that's what we read. So
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. מנא הני מילי mena
hanei milei *Mina hani mili*? Where do you know it? So yesterday
we talked about where you know the כהנים kohanim, *Kohanim* watch and
we had also not just watch on the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of
שערו ובנו בנו *Sha'aru vanu veno* so we know also לויים *Leviyim*
also from that פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. We also learned the לויים *Leviyim*
from the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of וילוו עליך alecha *veyilavu alecha* that
they would sometimes share a watch with the כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim*, the
כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* above, the לויים *Leviyim* below. But also there's a
question of where do you get twenty-one? Right we we learned of
three from the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* from one פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. Here
where do we get twenty-one? And again you know the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s working with an assumption that this is from the תורה Torah
*Torah* not just a a convention. So let's take a look. מנא
הני מילי *Mina hani mili*? Where did you get this these twenty-one
watches from? So אמר רב יהודה מסורא ואמרי לה במתניתא תנא *Amar
Rav Yehuda miSura ve'amri lah bemasnisa tana*. So רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*
from סורא *Sura* says and some say we taught in the ברייתא
Beraita, *Baraisa*. דכתיב *Dechasiv* the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says למזרח הלוים ששה
*Lemizrach HaLeviyim shisha*. Now this is a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in דברי
הימים Divrei Hayamim *Divrei HaYamim*. This פסוק *pasuk* in דברי הימים Divrei
Hayamim *Divrei HaYamim* basically is where it's very you know explicit and
clear about the different roles that the לויים *Leviyim* had. It lists
all the families of the לויים *Leviyim* that played the musical instruments
and then it lists all the families that watched the gates. And
those are the two functions of לויים *Leviyim*: משוררים *meshorerim*, the singers,
the music players, and the משוערים *meshoarim*, those that watch the gates.
And then at the end of listing all the families it said
here's where they were stationed, the לויים *Leviyim*. So it says למזרח
*lemizrach* on the east הלוים ששה *HaLeviyim shisha* there were six.
לצפונה *letzafona* on the north ללוים ארבעה *laLeviyim arba'ah* there were four
לויים *Leviyim*.
לנגבה *lanegba* the south ללוים ארבעה *laLeviyim arba'ah* there were four. לאסופים
*la'asufim* and to the אסופים
*asufim* which it's not exactly clear what it means but anyway
some say it means the chambers or the excuse me not the
chambers the
the antechambers שנים
שנים *shnayim shnayim* two two or two each.
לפרבר *laParbar* also not exactly clear what that means. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* will explain what it means in a minute but some translators
say it means something like the the portico. למערב ארבעה *lama'arav arba'ah*
to the west four למסילה *lamesilah*
I'm sorry לפרבר למערב ארבעה למסילה *laParbar lama'arav arba'ah lamesilah* four to
four for the like path leading up to this portico ושנים לפרבר
*ushnayim laParbar* and two for the actual portico itself or whatever this
פרבר *Parbar* means. Anyway so those are the various stations of לויים
*Leviyim*. Now the if you total them up they're close to twenty-one
but they're not, they're twenty-four. All right the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* never
actually going to worry about the twenty-four twenty-one, never actually tries to
worry about matching the exact locations with the locations we just listed
so I don't think that matches either right because this is east
to east, east to the west, doesn't exactly match the numbers that
the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* has. But anyway either way let's take a
look the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to focus on the total
number. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמי הני כ"ד הוו *Ami
hani chaf daled havu*. If you add that up that's twenty-four, it's
not it's not twenty-one. Right it was six and four right six
is ten... Then it was and four is 14. Two-two is 18
and then another six is 24. So אמר אביי Amar Abaye, *Amar
Abaye*, so אביי Abaye *Abaye* says הכי קאמר *hachi ka'amar*, this is
how to read it. לאסופים שנים *la'asufim shnayim*. When it says the
לאסופים *la'asufim*, again whatever that means, the antechamber, whatever it means, it
did when it says two-two, it really just meant two. Why did
it say two-two? So the מפרש *mefaresh* here says, well it's like
a way of ending a פסוק *pasuk* because actually the פסוק *pasuk*
does end שנים שנים *shnayim shnayim* and then the next פסוק *pasuk*
begins לפרבר למערב *laparbar lama'arav* etc. So he says if he really
wanted to say four it would have said four. So why did
it say two-two? It's just two. Everywhere it was two. Every time
they needed it there it was two. So it was really just
redundant, but it really is only two, not four. So that gets
you down to 22, but it's not 21. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says אכתי עשרין ותרי הוי *achti esrin utrei havei*, it's still
22, not 21. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says הכא דפרבר *hacha
deparbar*, when it says the פרבר *parbar*, which whatever that means, חד
הוה *chad havei*, it said two but it was really one. So
then why did it say two? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
ואחרינא בצוותא הוא דאזיל ויתיב גביה *vachrina betzavta hu de'azil veyatv gabeih*,
the other one was just to keep him company. Okay, really it
was only one לוי *Levi* that was on watch or one group.
And here it's clear again that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes one
means literally one. Again the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* uses this phrase עדה
*eidah*, but anyway here it sounds like it was literally one, but
he would get lonely. Okay, since he was there by himself, so
he had another guy to accompany him. He was the only one
that was single, so there were two people there but only one
was technically on watch.
We don't say that necessarily for the כהנים kohanim. *kohanim*, right? What?
If there was one כהן kohen *kohen*? Right. Well that's true.
That's also mentioned that the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* calls it an עדה
*eidah* of כהנים Kohanim *kohanim*. So exactly. Well also some of the
מפרשים *mefarshim* say that whatever this פרבר *parbar* was and wherever he
was, it was maybe somewhere that was very far away from everybody
else. So therefore maybe, I don't know, it doesn't match it up
to where to the places it says.
Why would they, why would the later rabbis doubt this as being
the real report when they say how do we know this? Why
do they need a פסוק *pasuk*? Isn't it possible that that was
the משנה Mishna, *Mishna*,
that that was just the convention and it was right? I agree.
It is definitely strange that it feels a need to base it
on a פסוק *pasuk*. And look, even if it's based on a
פסוק *pasuk* by דוד *David* in דברי הימים Divrei Hayamim *Divrei Hayamim*,
it's not based on a פסוק *pasuk* in the תורה Torah *Torah*.
So nothing is showing that it had to be this biblical or
this number is biblical. It could just be a convention.
And they had the reality of how they went to the bathroom
with the tunnel and they did with the clothes.
I agree. The best I could say, look, if it's trying to
tie it to a פסוק *pasuk*, so that in the תורה Torah
*Torah* you understand it wants to make it דאורייתא d'Oraita, *de'oraita*. But
this, the best I could say
is that
it wants to see continuity. Even if it's just a convention, it's
somehow more powerful if this is a convention that was always there
from the time of King David.
Why not accept it as an eyewitness reality?
Oh, they are accepting it as an eyewitness reality. No, no, they're
not, no, no, no. The question מנא לן *minalan* really is
where do we derive it from, not how do we know it
to be true? Meaning that this was the facts, we accept, but
where's it coming from? What's it based on? מנא לן *minalan* really
is more like what's it based on, not how do we know
it's true? And I think the reason they're asking what's it based
on, even if they're not going to a פסוק *pasuk* in the
תורה Torah *Torah*, is they want to see a sense of continuity.
You don't want to think like oh, in דוד's *David's* time the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash* was totally different, then they switched
it and then they did all of this. You want to see
that there's a sense of continuity. That's how I read it. But
מנא לן *minalan* really is not how do you know it's true,
but what's it based on? So that's really what they're asking. They're
accepting it as fact, but what's it based on? Where did it
come from? It came from a practice already from the time of
King David. That's what's going on. All right. All right, so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so this פרבר *parbar* wherever it was,
and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does not try to match this פסוק
*pasuk* up to the exact location that we have, was maybe some
say that it was very it was the furthest away, the most
isolated and therefore we gave him another guy to keep him company.
So חד הוה ובצוותא הוא דאזיל ויתיב גביה *chad havei uvetzavta hu
de'azil veyatv gabeih*, he would go and sit with him משום דקאי
אבראי *mishum deka'i abra'ei*, they were on the outside. Now all the
כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* around הר הבית Har Habayis. *Har Habayis* were on
the outside, but maybe it means particularly distant. מאי לפרבר *mai laparbar*?
What does that mean? אמר רבה בר רב שילא *Amar Rabba bar
Rav Sheila* כמאן דאמר כלפי בר *keman de'amar klapei bar*. So again,
using Aramaic to translate this word, כלפי *klapei* if you drop the
resh and you reverse the letters, towards the בר *bar*, towards the
outside. So this פרבר *parbar* was the furthest outpost of somebody that
was walking. Maybe it was at the part of the walls of
הר הבית Har Habayis. *Har Habayis* which were the most isolated from
traffic and the most away. So that's where he was.
What, why do you need a watch guy?
Why do you need any watch guy? It's all דרך כבוד kavod?
*derech kavod*. You don't want any part to be abandoned to be
without somebody watching. Okay. אמר רבה בר רב שילא *Amar Rabba bar
Rav Sheila* כמאן דאמר *keman de'amar* we just said it. ואי בעית
אימא V'i ba'it eima, *ve'iba'it eima*, so that's one way we see
21. It's 24, but you twiddle with the numbers and you get
it down to 21. ואי בעית אימא i ba'it eima, לעולם כ"ד
*ve'iba'it eima le'olam chaf daled*, it really is 24. דכתיב *dechtiv* תלתא
מניהו דכהנים *tlata mineihu dekohanim*, three of them are for the priests.
ועשרין וחד דלוים. That actually is very nice, right? 'Cause if you
have three of the כהנים Kohanim and the 21 of the לוים,
leviyim, you total 24. That פסוק by King David totals 24. So
we'll say that that's where we get the number 24 from. Okay?
Ah, that seemed to be all לוים? leviyim? No, some of those
were not just, were not לוים, leviyim, some of those were really
כהנים. Kohanim Alright. Now,
והא הכא לוים הוא דכתיב, v'ha hacha leviyim hu dich'tiv, but doesn't
it say לוים? leviyim? רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi,
like רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, דאמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי d'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi בכ"ד מקומות, b'chaf daled mekomot,
in 24 places, וארבע, v'arba, it's interesting, in 24 places נקראו כהנים
לוים. nikre'u kohanim leviyim. The כהנים Kohanim were called the לוים leviyim
because they are a subset of לוים, leviyim, so although the text
says לוים, leviyim, it's also referring, it's only or also referring to
the
כהנים. Kohanim וזה אחד מהם, v'zeh echad mehem, והכהנים הלוים בני צדוק,
v'hakohanim haleviyim b'nei tzadok, the כהנים, Kohanim the לוים, leviyim, those the
children of צדוק. Tzadok. Clearly they were כהנים, Kohanim but here it's
very explicit that you can also call them לוים. leviyim. So when
it says לוים leviyim were in 24 places, three of those were
the places of the כהנים. Now by the way, that does not
work, that works pretty well because three of the places were... oh
actually I'm sorry, no, hold on. No, that just says north and
south and east, forget it. Okay. So that's, so that's the other
answer. So we get this, seeing this as some continuity from what
they had at the time of King David. By the way, that
listing was not even yet around the מקדש, Mikdash, that was of
course the time of שלמה. Shlomo. The פסוקים psukim from דברי הימים
the time of David was also, was still when it was at
the sort of משכן Mishkan setup. But presumably that was again going
to be the model for, you know, the time of שלמה Shlomo
as well. Okay, so now the פסוק goes on.
חמישה וחמישה שערי הר הבית וארבע על ארבע פינותיו. chamisha v'chamisha sha'arei
Har Habayit v'arba al arba pinotav. Now we are going to look
more specifically at this משנה Mishna in מידות. Yes.
What did you just say about the time of שלמה? Shlomo?
That well, the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. wasn't built until the time
of שלמה. Shlomo. The פסוק here about the, about you know, the,
the 24 watches that we got from דברי הימים was a פסוק
from the time of King David. So it was really, but maybe
it was sort of pre-arranged in what it would be for when
they actually had a מקדש, Mikdash but the מקדש Mikdash, was not
yet there.
You're applying some of our framework from the earlier period?
As we certainly do, right.
As we were saying the other day, this diagram is just in...
Right, the diagram is בית שני. Bayit Sheni. But exactly, and it
goes back to Rivka's point, what we're trying to do though is
say, although this was בית שני Bayit Sheni and in some way
the architecture was different, we're trying to, you know, emphasize this continuity.
So a continuity to the בית ראשון, Bayit Rishon, continuity to the
פסוקים psukim by the משכן Mishkan and so on. So that's a
lot of what this מנא הני מילי is about.
So Rabbi, when it says that there are four on the four
corners, that's not defined by a wall, right? That's just randomly, you
know, if you just look at it in...
Why do you say that?
I'm just trying to understand where these four corners would be.
The four corners of the walls around הר הבית, Har Habayis? or
the four corners of the walls. Now when it says four corners
of the walls of the עזרה, Azara, that's not clear to me
because this is a corner on the inside but it's not a
corner on the outside. So I don't know, maybe they were these
four corners and that would also be, then they would be around
the, which would make sense, that they would be around the entire
walls of the עזרה, Azara not just, not you know, I mean
the entire outer walls as well. Until now we've been seeing that
the watches in the עזרה Azara were just this, the עזרה Azara?
here, not the עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim, But when it says four
corners, right, do you mean the inner corners and you're here, or
do you mean the outer corners? We're going to see that it
said when they were in the עזרה, Azara, they were on the
outside of the עזרה. Azara. So to say they were here and
here, it could be here and here or still, you know, but
I, it would make more sense if... So you're saying that at
the corners they were at these corners. But I'm assuming it literally
means they were at the, they were stationed at the corners. Did
they do some type of a סיבוב sivuv and walk a little
bit back and forth and they, you know, and so on, or
did they just stay, you know, stay at the corners without moving?
I don't know. But I don't know why not to assume it
means the four corners.
So it was all laid out as a, as corners? Like I
mean, it wasn't like, you know, it's a mountain, it's sort of
circular?
Yeah, but the walls were, but the walls were right angles. I
mean, I think you see that right now when you see the
excavations of the הר הבית, Har Habayis right? It's not a circular
wall, there are four walls, you know, they're angled walls around the
הר הבית. Har Habayis Okay, so now it goes on, it says
like this. So now we know from based on these פסוקים psukim
by דברי הימים the idea of 24. Now, חמישה וחמישה שערי הר
הבית. chamisha v'chamisha sha'arei Har Habayit. Now we're, now we're going back
to the משנה Mishna and talking about the specific places based on
the משנה Mishna where they were. Five on the five gates of
הר הבית, Har Habayis וארבע על ארבע פינותיו מתוכם. v'arba al arba
pinotav mitocham. And four on the four corners on the inside. And
this is presumably not on the inside of the gates, which you
could understand, but even the inside of the wall in terms of
the corners.
ה' שערי עזרה וארבע על ארבע פינותיו מבחוץ. Heh sha'arei Azarah v'arba
al arba pinotav mibachutz.
Now when it came to the לוים leviyim in the עזרה, Azarah?
there'd be five by the five gates. Remember again the לוים leviyim
would be at the bottom on some of these places, the כהנים
at the top, but you know, the כהנים anyway, the לוים leviyim
were in more places than the כהנים. They'd be at the five
gates and they'd also be on the four, in the four corners
מבחוץ, Mibachutz. on the outside. So that's first of all the point
that I was making is, so I get this corner and this
corner on the outside, but is it this... corner and this corner,
you know, then they're not positioned at something that's a visible corner.
So presumably, I'm guessing it means that it would be the corners
actually of the עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim.
Anyway, that's where they would be. So when it came to the
עזרה, Azarah. they were on the outside. When it came to the
הר הבית, Har Habayis they were on the inside. So now the
גמרא Gemara wants to know why the difference. So let's take a
look. מבחוץ. mibachutz מאי שנא Mai shna הר הבית Har Habayis? דעבדינן
d'avidina מתוכה, mitcha,
why
when it comes to the walls of הר הבית Har Habayis and
the gates are they on the inside? ומאי שנא U'mai shna עזרה,
Azara and why when it comes to the actual temple courtyard itself,
מבחוץ mibachutz, דעבדינן d'avidina מבחוץ, mibachutz,
they're watching on the outer gates and on the outside of the
gate and the outside of the wall? אמרי, Amri, the answer is,
you can say, הר הבית Har Habayis דאיתמא, de'itama,
when it comes to the Temple Mount, if you get weary, if
you get tired, ובעי למישב ubai l'meysev and you want to sit
take a rest, sit down—doesn't seem like
the—let me finish—יתיב, yasiv,
so you want to sit, ובעי למישב יתיב, ubai meysev yasiv, אמרינן
amrina we say, מתוכה, mitcha,
you can even be on the inside. Why? Or because you're allowed
to sit within, you know, in the environs of הר הבית. You
can sit if you're on הר הבית. So do it on the
inside, you can sit down. עזרה, Azara. when it comes to the
courtyard, temple courtyard, דאיתמא de'itama if you get tired ובעי ubai למישב
meysev and you want to sit, לא מצי יתיב, lo matzi yasiv,
you can't sit. Why? דאמר מר De'amar mar because we say, אין
ישיבה בעזרה אלא למלכי בית דוד בלבד. ein yeshiva b'azara ela l'malchei
beit david bilvad. The only people that can sit in the temple
courtyard proper are the kings of from the house of David. So
therefore since there would be no ability to sit if you were
on the inside, אמרינן amrina מבחוץ, we say do it on the
outside so we'll give you an opportunity to take a rest, to
sit down every now and then if you need to take a
break and you need to sit down. Okay so that's why we
do on the. Now of course what it also says is that
the natural inclination is to do it on the inside, but we'll
have you do it on the outside if we need to do
it in order to let you sit. So that doesn't exactly answer
why the default is to do it on the inside, right? Meaning
when it came to הר הבית, you could have been on the
inside, you could have been on the outer. Either way you could
sit. But we still say, you know, we'll have you do it
on the inside. So there certainly seems to be a default of
doing it on the inside unless that won't make you allow you
to sit and then do it on the outside. So that's not
exactly clear to me because again if you were to ask me
if you want to have a sort of like, you know, an
honor guard walking around to demonstrate, you know, the significance of the
place, you want it more visible, you want it more on the
outside than on the inside. So I don't really fully understand this
because again it assumes that there's a default of doing it on
the inside. The other point is,
and this gets to my question, if they really were watching on
the outside of the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim the four corners meant
the four corners of the including the עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, well
the prohibition of sitting is only in the the עזרה Azara proper,
right? Not the עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim So again if they were
at these corners they could have theoretically been on the inside here
because there's no prohibition of sitting here. So that again seems to
emphasize that the four corners really are the four corners of this
space, which makes it just a little ironic because when they're on
the outside of the wall here, they're not visibly at a corner.
I mean they're just at a midpoint. Do you understand? On the
inside they're at a corner. Am I being clear here? Yes. Okay.
Where can they not sit?
They can't sit in this עזרה Azara right from this black line
onward.
In the עזרת כהנים? Ezrat Kohanim?
Right. Yeah, exactly. So if they're on the—so if this is the
space they can't sit and they have to be on the outside,
so two of the four corners are not visible corners from the
outside. What?
I always thought this
the עזרת כהנים Ezrat Kohanim was a taller building.
No no no this is an open courtyard. That's an open courtyard.
It's all open.
The only thing that's roofed is this, is the היכל Heichal and
the דביר. Dvir. All of this because you need open air for
the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Right.
So possible these are two different levels of.
You mean maybe maybe there was still some little like here shows
like a little protrusion, you know, where the wall was.
A tower or a watchtower and then maybe the wall was even
higher.
Yeah, so I understand. It didn't look like a corner but you
maybe it was still visible. Like there was still some type of
a protrusion.
Would be a
corner if the wall was
higher there. Oh. Okay.
If this was six feet higher than this wall, yeah, you'd have
a square here and then you'd step down to get to this
square.
Alright anyway, a small corner, not a major right angle. Anyway.
Alright, so could you tell me which are those seven gates in
עזרה? Azara I still don't understand.
Where in the gate we haven't gotten up to it Michael. You
gotta little patience. Alright. No no no Michael, one thing at a
time. Okay, anyway. Alright, so that's the difference of the outside and
the inside. Again with the assuming we'll normally do the inside but
if you won't be allowed to sit, then we'll tell you to
do it on the outside. Okay now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
אמר מר, Amar mar, ה על ה שערי עזרה, he'el hay sha'arei
azara, five by the five gates of the עזרה, וה שערי—so v'hey
sha'arei by the five gates of the עזרה. So again this assumes
that all these chambers here have gates leading to the outside or
one of them has the gates on the inside. and all so
there would be לויים in front of each gate.
It says after Michael's question, וה' שערי הוא דהוו בעזרה, ve-hei sha'arei
hu d'havu ba'azarah, were only five gates in the
עזרה? רמינהי, Reminehu, שבעה שערי היו בעזרה, shiva'ah sha'arei hayu ba'azarah, there
were seven gates. ג' בצפון, gimmel be-tzafon, three in the north, וג'
בדרום, ve-gimmel be-darom, three in the south, ואחד במזרח, ve-echad ba-mizrach, one
in the east. So and presumably there are seven chambers. Most of
these pictures have seven chambers. Michael's picture has more than seven. How
many?
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine. I have a
bunch of these so I'm not even sure.
Well not everything they all say that they are gates. Not everything
that was a structure had a gate.
Well this is called here שער הנשים.
Yeah that yours looks like it has a picture of about eight
gates. Anyway whatever it
is so this... Right, mine is a little cut off. I see
one, two, three, oh great. Alright anyway I just don't have the
back one. Anyway let's keep on going.
Alright so let's take a look. Anyway so the normal tradition is
seven gates. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So how do you say five? אמר אביי, תרי מינייהו לא צריכי
שימור. trei mineihu lo tzrichi shimur. Yeah it's true there were seven
but they didn't need to watch all seven. They could've only they
could watch just five. Why? So the מפרש here says because well
look we look turned taught that the כהנים were three of the
places at least from above. So at least in two of the
places the כהנים watched so the לויים didn't have to watch. The
problem was was that it sounded like yesterday at least in one
place it said the כהנים and לויים were doing it in partnership,
right? The כהנים above the לויים below. And certainly the impression I
got was was that in all the places the כהנים and the
לויים were sort of you know in the three places that there
were כהנים there were also לויים below. So the רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu
Gershom and the רא"ש Rosh give a different answer. They say if
you watch the two outer ones you don't have to watch the
third one in the middle because then you've got like you know
coverage that way you know if you're on top of those gates
and you know you could be looking in both directions so you
have two pairs of eyes on the middle one.
I understand but you want to do it in a way that
makes sense. So that's אביי's answer. Yeah there were seven but but
they could do without watching five.
I saw eight in the picture.
Alright in somebody
nobody nobody this picture is not like in the גמרא Gemara that
somebody can go ask the גמרא Gemara why were there eight in
this picture. Let's keep on reading. Okay could everybody have a little
patience. Let's keep on reading. רבא אמר, Rava amar, תנאי, tana'ei, it's
a debate of תנאים. Tanna'im. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
Baraita: אין פוחתין מי"ג גזברין ומשבעה אמרכלין. ein pochtin mi-yud gimmel gizbarin
u-mi-shiva'ah amarkalin. You have no fewer than thirteen
like officers
and seven supervisors. Okay so
the גזברין gizbarin are like at a lower level. The אמרכלין amarkalin
are the head supervisors. So you know no fewer than that number
every day in the מקדש, Mikdash, you know in the בית אב.
Beit Av. So there's always going to be thirteen people sort of
you know sort of maybe floor managers and seven supervisors. ר' נתן
אומר, Rabbi Natan omer, where do you get this number from? אין
פוחתין מי"ג גזברין. ein pochtin mi-yud gimmel gizbarin. Where do you get
it
from? כנגד י"ג שערים keneged yud gimmel she'arim because thirteen the thirteen
floor managers is equal to the thirteen gates that there was in
in you know in the מקדש Mikdash complex. Now how do you
get thirteen gates? חמשה דהר הבית, chamishah d'Har ha-Bayit, we mentioned that
there were five of the Temple Mount. So how much are you
left with? פשלו להו תמניא דעזרה, pashlu lehu tamnya d'azarah, there would
be eight in the עזרה. So he says look you see implicit
in ר' נתן's Rabbi Natan statement that he assumed that there were
eight gates. Now of course that also assumes that there were no
gates in terms of the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim which is interesting.
But
anyway אלמא, alma, so anyway so you see that there's an opinion
you're telling me five, seven.
אלמא איכא תנא דאמר תמניא הוו. alma ika tanna de-amar tamnya havu.
You see that there are those that say eight. So if there
are those that say eight, איכא תנא דאמר שבעה, ika tanna de-amar
shiva'ah, there are those who say seven, ואיכא תנא דאמר חמשה הוו,
ve-ika tanna de-amar chamishah havu, there are those that say five. So
fine there's a debate. What else is new in life? There's a
debate. Now of course what is new is is that as I
mentioned to you our you never have you don't have it articulated
as a debate. This is not about הלכה, halacha, this is about
fact historically, right? And you don't have all of this stuff is
pretty much סתם. stam. Even ר' נתן Rabbi Natan is not voicing
what he's saying as a different opinion. So it's not so פשוט
pashut to attribute these things to debates because maybe this was largely
accepted fact you know and we try to say that there wouldn't
be so many debates in the actual fact. But nevertheless the גמרא
Gemara says it's a debate. You know it all also could be
a question about what do you call a gate? You call that
a gate? That's not a gate. That's just a little door. Okay.
So anyway but the גמרא Gemara saying that maybe there is a
question exactly how many gates there were, what exactly you called the
gates and this report had five and then there are other versions
as well.
Is it possible remembering different versions of the Temple?
It could also just be that there's an actual well that's what
the גמרא Gemara sounds like saying there's an actual debate of fact.
You know like one temple had seven, the next temple had eight.
How many temples do you think there were? What one guy remembers
from fifteen hundred years ago, and then there's another tradition.
Maybe.
Alright none of these are in the פסוקים pesukim like how many
gates there
were?
Wait, what פסוקים Pesukim by the בית שני? Bayit Sheni? Anyway, so
now the גמרא goes on, so that was, so that was now
where the לויים watched, and that's from the beginning of מדות, Middot,
which is a good thing since we have no גמרא on מדות,
Middot, now we've at least dealt with it so when we'll, so
in תמיד Tamid? when we get to מדות Middot we'll have already
dealt with it.
Now moving on, let me just take a few questions
here.
Moving on to our משנה, back to our משנה. So our משנה
listed where they slept and the different rooms, excuse me, where they
watched, the different rooms, and then it said that when they slept
in the בית המוקד, they slept, they took off, you know, their
clothes, they slept in their own clothes, not in the בגדי קודש,
Bigdei Kodesh, and they put their בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehuna, you know,
under their head. So the גמרא is now going to focus on
that. I should, by the way, mention that although it sounds like
all the כהנים that were going to work the next day slept
in that room, because remember it says that the guy came and
knocked on the door and then they took the, whatever, you know,
the lottery, the רמב"ם Rambam emphasizes that it was the כהנים who
were on watch, or at least on watch in that room, slept
in that room. Again, if they're on watch, why are they sleeping?
You'd be on some rotation. I also saw an interesting thing in
the רמב"ם I wanted to mention. We saw yesterday that the person
who came for the lottery, actually we saw in the משנה, that
the person who came for the lottery, right, knocked on the door
and then he had them do the lottery. From the רמב"ם it
sounds what happens is that he wasn't sleeping in the בית המקדש.
Beis Ha-Mikdash He wasn't necessarily specific to that day. So he came
from the outside. He knocked on the outside door. They opened the
door for him. He didn't have the keys. Okay? They were on
the inside with the keys. He knocked on the outside door, they
opened the door for him, then they gave him the keys, then
he opened the keys into the מקדש, and then they all went
out and then they, you know, and then they started their day
of work. Anyway, let's take a look now. It says so that
when they were sleeping there they had their clothes under their head.
שינה הוא דלא, Sheina hu dlo, so it says they would not
sleep in the בגדי קודש, Bigdei Kodesh,
בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehuna, אבל הלוך מהלכין, aval hiluch mahalachin, but it
sounds like they'd be allowed to walk around in it even if
they're not doing the עבודה. Avoda. So שמע מינה, Shma mina, can
we infer from this, בגדי כהונה ניתנו ליהנות בהן, Bigdei Kehuna nitnu
lhenot bahen, that you can derive benefit from the בגדי כהונה? Bigdei
Kehuna? Right, we just finished a whole מסכת Masechet about מעילה, Meila,
of not deriving benefit from things that are sanctified. Well, one of
the things that were sanctified was בגדי כהונה. Bigdei Kehuna. So while
they were wearing it during the עבודה, Avoda, that was not considered
their personal benefit; that was something that was part of, required in
terms of the עבודה. Avoda. But what if after they're done with
their עבודה, Avoda, do they have to take it off immediately? Because
to use it as soon as they step out of the מקדש,
they're now sort of, you know, using it for their personal benefit,
personal pleasure, or not? So logically you would say yes, it's a
מעילה Meila problem, but there actually is an opinion that ניתנו ליהנות
בהן, nitnu lhenot bahen, that when they were originally sanctified, they were
sanctified with the stipulation that the כהן kohen? actually could derive personal
benefit from them. Presumably not that they wanted them to walk around
and to go to the gym with them on or whatever, but,
you know, so that they wouldn't have to worry that like if
they kept them on a second too long that they would be
עובר over on מעילה. Meila. You know, so that's the question. So
it sounds like, okay, sleeping no, but walking around yes. So אמר
ליה, Amar lei, הוא הדין אפילו הילוך נמי לא. hu hadin afilu
hiluch nami lo. You could say that even walking around they weren't
allowed to do in them. והאי דקתני ישנים, Vhai dkatani yeshenim, so
why did it say they didn't sleep in them? משום דבעי למתני
סיפא, mishum dbaei lmitni seifa, the end is going to say, אלא
פושטין ומקפלין ומניחין אותן תחת ראשיהן. ela poshtin umikaplin umanichin otan tachat
rosheihen. It wanted to tell you what they did with them. It
wanted to tell you they took them off, they folded them, they
put them under their head. So it's explaining they didn't sleep with
them. They didn't sleep; it's just descriptive. It's not to infer, "Ah,
they couldn't sleep, they could do something else." No, they could have
done a lot of things with them, but we're talking about going
to sleep, so we're saying they couldn't sleep in them. So don't
try to infer from that that there's something that they could do
other things with them. So דקתני רישא נמי לא היו ישנים, Dkatani
reisha nami lo hayu yeshenim, so it also says they didn't sleep,
but it's not to tell to infer that other things could. It's
just describing what happened when they were going to sleep. So the
גמרא says, והא גופא קשיא, Vha gufa kashya, so finally it asks
about that description itself. ומניחין אותן תחת ראשיהן, Umanichin otan tachat rosheihen,
it says they would put it under their head, presumably they'd use
it as a pillow. How could they use it as a pillow?
It's בגדי כהונה. Bigdei Kehuna. שמע מינה בגדי כהונה ניתנו ליהנות בהן,
Shma mina Bigdei Kehuna nitnu lhenot bahen, we can infer that they
can derive benefit because they put it under their head. So no,
אימא, eima, it doesn't mean under their head. It means כנגד ראשיהן,
keneged rosheihen, near their head. You know, they kept it there, but
it doesn't mean they actually used it. So of course תחת תחת
ממש.
tachat
tachat mamash.
What? תחת ההר, Tachat hahar, by the foot of. That's an interesting
point.
Anyway, so אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, so first of all
stretch of the words, but even if you say that, the problem
is if it's right near your head and you're asleep at night,
it's not so unlikely that you'll roll over and use it as
a pillow. So רב פפא Rav Papa learns something from this. אמר
רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, שמע מינה, shma mina, from this we
can
infer, תפילין מן הצד שריין. tefillin min hatzad sharyon. ולא חיישינן דילמא
מיגנדר ונפל עלייהו. Vlo chayshinan dilma mignadar vnafal aleihu. If you go
to sleep or you want to take a nap, right, you're not
allowed to nap with your תפילין tefillin on
because you'll pass gas. So you take off your תפילין. tefillin. So
can you take off your תפילין tefillin and put it right down
near your head when you put your head down on the table
to go to sleep or lie down to go to sleep? He
says, presumably yes. Logically you would say maybe not, because you'll roll
over and you'll lie on top of it; it would not be
respectful. But if you're not concerned about that by בגדי כהונה Bigdei
Kehuna where there's a biblical prohibition of deriving... benefit of מעילה, Me'ilah,
and we would allow them to have the בגדי כהונה Bigdei Kehunah
near their head, so we could say that you could allow them
also by the תפילין. Tefillin. Now by the way, it's not just
an analogy; it is an analogy, but the analogy is important because
in a number of places there is a constant sort of drawing
of a parallel between תפילין Tefillin and בגדי כהונה. Bigdei Kehunah. Often
it's the תפילין Tefillin and the ציץ, Tzitz, but it's a certain
sense of wearing something that gives us a sense of like קדושה
kedusha and elevation and thinking about God and so on. There's a
little bit about that also by the ציצית Tzitzit as well. So
it's not just an analogy; there's some power to that comparison of
תפילין Tefillin and בגדי כהונה. Bigdei Kehunah. Okay, so that's what Rav
Papa says. So now we're saying: טלית Tallis or ציצית? Tzitzis?
Well, the גמרא didn't really have a special בגד beged of טלית,
Tallis, so it means whatever בגד beged was wearing the ציצית. Tzitzit.
So now, okay, so now Rav Papa so anyway, so we now
have said that you're not allowed to derive benefit. It meant near
their head, and from that we can derive that we're not concerned
that you'll roll over and put your head on it, which seems
to be a pretty reasonable thing to be concerned about. So the
גמרא says: הכי נמי מסתברא. Hachi nami mistabra. You know what? It
makes sense that it wasn't really under their head, even forgetting the
question about the קדושה kedusha and whether they could derive benefit. Why?
דכנגד ראשיהם, Di-kenegged rasheihem, that it was only opposite their head. דאי
אמרת תחת ראשיהם, De-ei amrat tachat rasheihem, under their head, נהי דניתנו
ליהנות בהן, nehi denitnu lehanot bahen, even if you were to say
you could derive benefit from בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehunah, תיפוק ליה משום
איסור דכלאים. teipokei lei mishum issur de-kilayim. What about the problem of
שעטנז? shatnez? Because the belt of the כהן, kohen, and actually we're
going to see that's debated, but it's quite possible that the belt
of the כהן kohen was made with wool and linen. So it's
שעטנז. shatnez. Now, of course, okay, the תורה Torah allows you to
do it when you're wearing the בגדי כהונה. Bigdei Kehunah. But as
soon as you're no longer doing the מצוה mitzvah of wearing בגדי
כהונה, Bigdei Kehunah, even if there's not a קדושה kedusha. problem, there's
an איסור issur of putting שעטנז shatnez on you. So how could
they have put it under their head literally? That would be like
a pillow of שעטנז shatnez and it's not when they're doing the
מצוה mitzvah of wearing the בגדי כהונה. Bigdei Kehunah. So obviously it
does not mean under their head; obviously it means near their head.
They could have just
taken off everything except the belt.
What? Well, the גמרא is going to get to that. Okay, so
the
גמרא says: הניחא למאן דאמר אבנטו של כהן גדול לא זהו אבנטו
של כהן הדיוט. haniha le-man de-amar avneto shel Kohen Gadol lo zehu
avneto shel Kohen Hedyot.
You could get out of this point if you were to say
that the belt of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is not the
same as the belt of the כהן הדיוט. Kohen Hedyot. The belt
of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was clear that that was made
out of שעטנז. shatnez. Okay, we're not going to go into here
how they learn it from the פסוקים, pesukim, how they assume it,
but everybody agrees that the belt of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
was made from שעטנז. shatnez. The question was, what was the story
of the belt of a normal כהן? Kohen So if you say
it wasn't the same as the belt of a normal כהן, and
the normal כהן was not שעטנז, shatnez, fine, then that proof goes
away and maybe they literally did use it as a pillow. אלא
למאן דאמר אבנטו של כהן הדיוט זהו אבנטו של כהן גדול, Ella
le-man de-amar avneto shel Kohen Hedyot zehu avneto shel Kohen Gadol, if
it was the same as the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, it was
out of שעטנז, shatnez, not the same physical belt but the same
material, made the same, then it was out of שעטנז, shatnez, so
obviously it can't mean under their head, it must mean near their
head. מאי איכא למימר? Mai ikka le-meimar? What can you say? So
you see it means near their head. So the גמרא says: No,
maybe I have another way of saying that they could have used
it as a pillow without a שעטנז shatnez problem. Why?
דכי תימא כלאים בהעלאה ובלבישה
הוא דאסור. De-chi teima kilayim be-ha'alah u-velivishah hu de-assur. כלאים kilayim maybe
is only prohibited to put on you and to wear. What are
the פסוקים pesukim by כלאים? kilayim? Two פסוקים. pesukim. One פסוק is
לא תלבש שעטנז צמר ופשתים יחדיו, lo tilbash shatnez tzemer u-fishtim yachdav,
do not wear שעטנז, shatnez, and the other wool and linen together.
The other פסוק says ובגד כלאים שעטנז לא יעלה עליך, u-veged kilayim
shatnez lo ya'aleh alecha,
shall not be put upon you. So I'm not wearing a pillow;
it's not on top of me; it's under me. Maybe it's not
a problem. Okay, so the way the גמרא in one place actually
describes this is it's about also getting some type of הנאת חימום,
hana'at himum, like it's warming you. When it's underneath you, okay, it's
comfortable, whatever, but it's not providing warmth like a normal garment that's
on top of you provides warmth. Okay, so maybe that's why it's
okay; maybe it is שעטנז shatnez and it's still okay. אבל ממכתו
תתי, Aval memachto tatei, to put it underneath you, to lay it
underneath you, שפיר דמי, shapir dami, that would be okay. והתניא? Ve-ha
tanya? So you can't say that because we say the following. That's
not a way out of it because we've taught in a ברייתא:
Braisa לא יעלה עליך, lo ya'aleh alecha, that שעטנז shatnez shall not
be placed upon you. אבל אתה מציעו תחתיך. Aval atta matzio tachtecha.
In theory, you can lay it underneath you like as a blanket.
אבל אמרו
חכמים, Aval ameru chachamim, although that's biblically true, so it's a good
point דאורייתא, d'Oraita but rabbinically we say the Rabbis say, אסור לעשות
כן, assur la'asot ken, we don't allow you to do that. שמא
תכרך נימא אחת על בשרו, Shema tichrach nima achat al besaro, because
what will happen is that one little string
will be a stray string and it will go on top of
you and not just remain under you and warm you. You'll get
a tiny minuscule amount of warmth by that, and it would actually
have to be a string that was actually a blend string, anyway,
and therefore they did not let you use it as a pillow.
The assumption here is There is, you know. Now here, of course,
I'm waiting for Michael to ask, oh, don't we say like אין
שבות במקדש, Ein Shvus BaMikdash, like we don't normally have rabbinic restrictions?
But it's important to... okay fine, Charlie would have said that if
he was here. It's important to know that that point is not,
is not blanket and categorical. It means that we don't have rabbinic
restrictions when they get in the way of the efficient doing of
the עבודה. Avodah. It doesn't mean we have absolutely no rabbinic restrictions.
So this does not get in the way of doing the עבודה;
Avodah; don't use this as your pillow, you know. And therefore, therefore
we're saying we cannot literally mean they had it under their head
because at least rabbinically they wouldn't have been able to do that
because of the איסור issur of כלאים. kilayim.
The גמרא also says that interestingly,
you know, usually you say like you have to have like a
שיעור shiur of הנאה, hana'ah, like whatever it is, like שפופרת, sh'poperet,
הנאה hana'ah is not like, you know, you get the idea.
Yeah, it's an interesting question about, you know, I mean here it's
a question about בגד, beged, it's not a שיעור, shiur, it's just
having the בגד beged on you. It's not an איסור הנאה, issur
hana'ah, it's an איסור issur of putting the בגד beged on you.
But to define as being on you is that it's עליך and
that there's some הנאה hana'ah from it. It's sort of the function
that it's playing, that's what's אסור. assur It's not אסור as the
הנאה, hana'ah, okay?
But at the end, anyway, you would rather be cool and you're
saying you get no הנאה hana'ah from that?
I mean, yes, but it's not really about... I mean there are
some interesting questions about that, about there's a משנה about wearing כלאים
kilayim when you're doing it for... there's some interesting discussion about the
שעטנז shatnez but not, not for us yet.
Why would they make a distinction between getting comfort from using it
as a pillow and especially on a cold stone floor?
Right, so that's what I said to Michael, it's not an איסור
הנאה. issur hana'ah. It's not like you can't derive benefit from שעטנז.
shatnez. I mean, I could be in the שעטנז shatnez business and
derive...
you can't put it on.
You can't put it on. So the definition of putting it on,
you know, is through this.
Okay, so right now where are we with this?
We are saying that we're trying to prove it doesn't literally mean
under their head, and one of the proofs is you obviously couldn't
do it regardless of can you derive benefit from בגדי כהונה bigdei
kehuna because it's שעטנז. shatnez. And even though it's not a דאורייתא
problem, at least rabbinically they wouldn't have been able to use it
as a pillow. So clearly it doesn't mean literally under their head.
וכי תימא דמפסיק מידי, v'chi teima demifsak midi, maybe
they didn't have it directly touching their head? They had it as
like the padding and they had, you know, something else directly under
their head, so there'd be no concern that a string from the
שעטנז, shatnez, like it was שעטנז shatnez stuffing in a pillow. There
would be no concern that the string would actually get onto their
skin
directly. So ואמר רב שמעון אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי אמר רבי
יוסי בן שאול משום קהלא קדישא שביירושלים. V'amar Rav Shimon amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi amar Rabbi Yosi ben Shaul mishum Kehala Kadisha shebiY'rushalayim.
That's interesting. So don't we have a tradition in the name of
Rav Shimon in the name of Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi in the
name of Rabbi Yosi ben Shaul in the name of the holy
congregation in Jerusalem? I don't know what, you know, what exactly that
refers to, right? I don't know, they were rabbis, it was a
tradition, you know, anyway, a community they all shoal? Anyway, אפילו עשר
מצעות זו על גב זו, afilu eser matza'ot zu al gav zu,
even if you had ten blankets, you know, one on top of
the other, וכלאים תחתיהם, v'kilayim tachteichem, and כלאים kilayim was underneath them,
אסור לישן עליהם. assur lishon aleihem. It's the princess and the pea,
right? It's sort of like... exactly. It also is sort of, by
the way, this whole idea of the ten things, it's also because
that same sort of metaphor is used by the idea of the
טומאת משכב ומושב tumat mishkav u'moshav of a זב וזבה. zav v'zava.
So it says that even if they're on the top and there're
ten things, even the thing on the very most bottom becomes טמא.
So one wonders if that served as the model. But anyway, once
rabbinically we say don't use it, we say don't use it even
if you have something that interrupts. This thing cannot be used as
a pillow regardless of if it's in direct contact with your body
or not. So you see that they could not have used it
as a pillow. אלא שמע מינה נגד ראשיהם. Ela shma mina neged
rasheihem. You see it doesn't literally mean under their head, it means
near their head. So the whole thing is clearly means near their
head and isn't relevant for the discussion of whether you can derive
benefit from בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. So that's one sort of take.
ואי בעית אימא, i ba'it eima if you want though you could
say, it's not so much an ואי בעית אימא, ואי בעית אימא
usually means sort of like an equivalent answer. This is more like
rejecting the point, and this goes back to what David says, באבנט
שאין בו כלאים. be'avnet she'ein bo kilayim. Maybe actually they did have
it under their head, so they just didn't use the belt. They
used the other parts of them, right? It was one belt. They
had the whole outer garment, they had the hat. So fine, they
didn't use the belt. That was the only thing that had כלאים.
kilayim. So we don't really know. Can you prove from the שעטנז
shatnez point that they did not use it as a pillow? Not
necessarily. Number one, maybe the belt wasn't שעטנז. shatnez. Number two, even
if the belt was שעטנז, shatnez, maybe they didn't use the belt.
So if it was just the שעטנז shatnez point, maybe they did
use it as a pillow. Maybe it is literal. And then it
really gets to the question of can you derive benefit from בגדי
כהונה bigdei kehuna or not, do we interpret the statement of under
their head literally or not. Yes.
So what about, forget about drawing benefit from it, but if you
know, we're having all these watches משום זה כבוד mishum zeh kavod
and all that, we're clearly concerned about the honor of the בית
המקדש. Why shouldn't we be concerned about the... you know, this doesn't
seem too honorable to be using the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna as
a pillow. So I mean, what about like just...
I agree with you. I agree with you. You know, but... I
don't know. I'm... you're right. You're right. I don't know. It's a
good point. I agree with you, but the גמרא wouldn't be able
to prove it from that, but you're just saying shouldn't that... be
like intuitive but you can't prove your point that that proves that
it wasn't the case. רב אשי אמר בגדי כהונה קשים הן דאמר
רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע. Rav Ashi Amar Bigdei Kehuna Kashim Hein
De-Amar Rav Huna Beray De-Rav Yehoshua. The בגדי כהונה Bigdei Kehuna were
hard, they were stiff, it was like it wasn't like a cloth
belt, it was made out of cloth but it was a very
stiff cloth. It was more like sort of like the so it
was very sort of had the consistency of like a leather type
of a belt, it was stiff. And therefore because רב הונא בריה
דרב יהושע Rav Huna Beray De-Rav Yehoshua says: הנמטא גמדא דנרש שריא.
Ha-Namta Gamda De-Narsh Sharya.
So this sort of like felt
material, so הנמטא Namta is like a felt and גמדא Gamda is
hard, this hard felt of נרש Narsh which was a place is
permissible. That you actually can put, use as a pillow or sit
on and it was כלאים. Kilayim. So it's quite ironic right, if
it's soft then even if it's a stuffed inside of an outer
shell and under ten things it's forbidden. Because once it's soft we
say ah this is soft and in theory it could be on
your skin, it could go on your skin then you can't use
it no matter how many separations you put. But if it's a
very stiff type of a fabric and there's no way that it
could get on top of your skin because it's very hard and
stiff and immovable, so in that type of in that situation we
do allow it even though it's שעטנז. Shatnez. So it will never
get on you, allow you to sit on it because it will
never be get on top of your skin and warm you and
so on.
Okay, so now
we're saying maybe they did sleep on the belts and the belts
were stiff and they would therefore be no concern that a little
string would come on top of their skin.
And the other
stuff didn't have כלאים Kilayim anyway. So we have now a couple
of answers. Can't we prove that it doesn't mean under their head?
No. Maybe it was under their head. Maybe A it wasn't כלאים.
Kilayim. Maybe it was under their head and they didn't have the
belt there. And even if they had the belt there, maybe the
belt was stiff and since it was under their head there wasn't
there was not even a rabbinic problem because
they're not actually wearing it.
Exactly, exactly. Okay now the next about eight lines are taken out
as you'll see because this סוגיא Sugya is parallel in another גמרא
in יומא Yoma and I'll just read it to you quickly because
this is really like cut and pasted from there and doesn't belong
here, but I'll read it to you quickly because it's interesting because
you'll see that it's the nature of this as a gloss. So
we'll just read this stuff quickly in parentheses: תא שמע בגדי כהונה
היוצא בהן למדינה אסור במקדש בין בשעת עבודה בין שלא בשעת עבודה
מותר מפני שבגדי כהונה ניתנו ליהנות בהן. Ta Shema Bigdei Kehuna Ha-Yotzei
Ba-Hen La-Medina Assur Ba-Mikdash Bein Be-Sha'at Avoda Bein She-Lo Be-Sha'at Avoda Muttar
Mi-Pnei She-Bigdei Kehuna Nitnu Le-Hehanos Ba-Hen.
So there's actually a ברייתא Braisa that says don't go out and
wear it in the street, the בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehuna, but you
can wear it in the בית המקדש even when you're not doing
the עבודה Avoda because
you're allowed to derive
benefit. שמע מינה. Shema Mina.
So that's a good proof that according to that ברייתא Braisa. certainly
you're allowed to derive benefit. And then it says ובמדינה לא, U-Ba-Medina
Lo, is it really true you couldn't wear it out on the
street? והתניא בכ"ה בו ביום הרגריזים דלא למספד. Ve-Ha-Tanya Be-Chaf Heh Bo
Ba-Yom Har Gerizim De-Lo Limsapad.
And then it quotes a statement from מסכת תענית Masechet Taanis that
tries to disprove it. And then the end says like and then
it says
whatever because we haven't quoted the whole thing. כי אתא ביומא פרק
בא לו כהן גדול, Ki Ata Be-Yoma Perek Ba Lo Kohen Gadol,
go see the סוגיא Sugya over there, this is the rest of
the סוגיא Sugya in יומא Yoma in the פרק בא לו כהן
גדול. Perek Ba Lo Kohen Gadol. Ad dot dot dot and take
copy from that סוגיא, Sugya, or that סוגיא Sugya goes until the
line איבעית אימא ראוין הן לבגדי כהונה ואיבעית אימא עת לעשות להשם
הפרו תורתך. I-Ba-Is Teima Rauyin Hein Le-Bigdei Kehuna Ve-I-Ba-Is Teima Es La-Asos
La-Hashem Heferu Torasecha. So this is something that you get that copyists
actually would not copy, if you had a parallel section they would
actually not bother to copy it down the whole second time. They
would just say go over there, go get the text from over
there and it's the same text here. Okay and that leads to
a lot of confusion. Sometimes that gloss would get lost, sometimes it
wasn't the exact same text, etc. Here it seems like they saw
a parallel and they said oh look the rest of the סוגיא
Sugya is over there, but actually it wasn't really directly relevant to
the discussion here so most assume that this doesn't belong here. Although
what you do see at least from the little allusion to that
סוגיא, Sugya, the little quote, is that there are explicit statements that
בגדי כהונה Bigdei Kehuna are ניתנו ליהנות בהם. Nitnu Le-Hehanos Ba-Hem. You
can derive benefit, but it doesn't necessarily mean you can wear them
as your street clothes.
But what was the answer then? איבעית אימא ראוין הן לבגדי כהונה
ואיבעית אימא עת לעשות להשם הפרו תורתך.
I-Ba-Is Teima Rauyin Hein Le-Bigdei Kehuna Ve-I-Ba-Is Teima Es La-Asos
La-Hashem Heferu Torasecha.
You can go look there. Go look there. Okay. All right moving
on. So what we've done now is was he
a כהן and he was doing sacrifice stuff would he wear בגדי
כהונה Bigdei Kehuna or not?
No. No. But in the temple even not doing the עבודה Avoda
at least that's the ברייתא. Baraisa, So now what we've done is
we've seen number one that the לויים would watch in twenty-one places
around הר הבית on the inside, around the עזרה on the outside.
Now we've seen that they would sleep with their clothes at near
their head, not under their head although it sounds like under their
head a little bit debated, either the שעטנז Shatnez problem but maybe
not. Maybe the belt wasn't שעטנז. Shatnez. Maybe even if it was,
it was hard or and so on. And the other and then
right and then the question of on top of which which is
whether you can derive benefit from בגדי כהונה Bigdei Kehuna at least
when you're in the מקדש area proper. Okay now we go on.
Where are we? All right so it says like this: אירע קרי
באחד מהם, Ira Keri Be-Achad Me-Hem, one of them became a בעל
קרי, ba'al keri what would he do? he would go through a
tunnel, go to the מקוה, mikvah, wait till the next morning. So
מסייע ליה לרבי יוחנן, mesayei lei l'Rebbi Yochanan, this supports Rebbi Yochanan,
דאמר מחילות לא נתקדשו, d'amar mechilos lo niskadshu,
that the tunnels were not sanctified, right? Because or else what would
have been the purpose of going through a tunnel? The very fact
that you're going through a tunnel proves that they weren't sanctified and
that's why you would want to go that way in order so
that you would not be on Temple grounds when you were going
through the עזרה. And we also see ובעל קרי משתלח חוץ לשני
מחנות, u'ba'al keri mishtale'ach chutz l'shnei machanos,
that a בעל קרי ba'al keri. would have to be sent out
of two camps. Because in the תורה this is you know they
model pattern the zones after in ירושלים Yerushalayim after the zones that
were in the you know in the in סיני Sinai in the
משכן. Mishkan. So in the משכן Mishkan there was the מחנה כהונה,
Machaneh Kehunah, which was the משכן Mishkan itself, then there was the
מחנה לויה, Machaneh Leviyah, which was the לוים Leviim that were encamped
around the משכן, Mishkan, and that was the second camp. And the
third camp was מחנה ישראל, Machaneh Yisrael, right the whole camp that
was in around them. In that translated to ירושלים Yerushalayim is the
actual עזרה was the מחנה שכינה, Machaneh Shchina, the הר הבית was
מחנה לויה, Machaneh Leviyah, not the עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim and עזרת
נשים was part of מחנה לויה, Machaneh Leviyah, and ירושלים Yerushalayim was
מחנה ישראל. Machaneh Yisrael. So the בעל קרי ba'al keri is sent
the only person sent out of all three camps is the מצורע
metzora because it's בדד ישב, badad yesheiv, he's completely out of the
camp. That's why we need the הפטרה haftorah by מצורע metzora by
ארבעה מצורעים arba'ah metzoraim right they were outside of the city, ארבע
sorry ארבע they were outside of the city. Okay by the way
though that city wasn't ירושלים Yerushalayim because any walled city had the
same status of מחנה ישראל Machaneh Yisrael but I don't want to
get into that. Now the other level the next level as I
said were people that had טומאה tumah that came from their
body. זב, zav, זבה, zava, נדה, niddah, and although the תורה doesn't
say חז"ל Chazal understand included in זב zav is בעל קרי. ba'al
keri So that would be out of מחנה לויה Machaneh Leviyah which
would be out of הר הבית. So since when they were in
this room they were really only the room they were in the
half that was towards the outside they were only in קדושת הר
הבית kedushas Har Habayis מחנה לויה Machaneh Leviyah not in מחנה שכינה
Machaneh Shchina and nevertheless you had to do this whole thing about
tunnels and trying to avoid and whatever shows that even a בעל
קרי ba'al keri is not allowed is sent out of two camps.
He's not allowed he's just like a זב zav and he also
is not allowed in מחנה לויה Machaneh Leviyah not only not in
the עזרה proper but not even in מחנה לויה Machaneh Leviyah can't
even be on הר הבית.
Which would imply this tunnel had a terminus at the outside so
he can
go all the way out or or the מקוה mikva itself was
underground. If the מקוה mikva itself was underground then he remained under
the temple for the whole day? No the problem is that even
after he's טובל tovel why did we let him go back? Okay
that the גמרא isn't discussing now then he was no longer בעל
קרי ba'al keri proper he was a טבול יום. tvul yom And
then that gets to the question about is a טבול יום tvul
yom is prohibited in הר הבית? A טבול יום tvul yom is
actually also prohibited in עזרת נשים so not just the I mean
but actually that excuse me not just עזרת נשים I'm saying that
goes without saying. He's prohibited in all of הר הבית a טבול
יום tvul yom. of a בעל קרי ba'al keri you know the
same way the person themselves the זב zav זבה zava נדה niddah
are אסור in הר הבית the טבול יום tvul yom of זב
zav זבה zava נדה niddah בעל קרי ba'al keri is אסור in
הר הבית but that's a question whether it's rabbinic or biblical. Okay
so then so but the גמרא is not getting into that. Okay
so before we get to him going to the מקוה mikvah let's
just read that again. If אמר רב ספרא amar Rav Safra so
let's just read that again. מסייע ליה לרבי יוחנן דאמר מחילות לא
נתקדשו. mesayei lei l'Rebbi Yochanan d'amar mechilos lo niskadshu.
Number one the fact that he went into a tunnel and he
had to go into a tunnel shows
that the tunnel solved the problem. It could only solve the problem
if they didn't have the קדושה. kedusha. Okay so א it shows
that. But it also shows that there was a problem that needed
to be solved. And why was the problem that needed to be
solved? He was in the outer half he was sleeping obviously he
wasn't in the עזרה proper he was in the הר הבית קדושה.
So why were there problems? So what we can also infer is
ובעל קרי משתלח חוץ לשני מחנות u'ba'al keri mishtale'ach chutz l'shnei machanos
that
even though he was a בעל קרי he wasn't a זב zav
the תורה only says זב zav nevertheless a בעל קרי is like
a זב zav טומאה יוצא מגופו tumah yozei migufo and even he
had to be out of מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah. So how's he
going to get out of מחנה לויה? Machaneh Leviyah? How's he going
to get off of הר הבית? He goes into the tunnel. Okay
then the only remaining question is okay but even if he's gone
to the מקוה mikvah he's a טבול יום. tvul yom Okay and
therefore the easiest answer is fine but being a טבול יום that's
only rabbinic and therefore we let him stay until the morning.
Does the tunnel have an exit both out- That's what Michael was
asking.
I would say maybe it just has a maybe the מקוה's mikva
underground. Yeah but then- So then you did everything underground. And then
once he's טובל tovel he's a טבול- No then we said as
a טבול יום we let him stay on הר הבית until the
next morning. So the question is why? So the simplest answer is
is that טבול יום's problem on הר הבית is only rabbinic. It's
not biblical. Okay so that's that. That's going to the מקוה. mikvah.
Now we talk about the tunnel and the bathroom. ונרות דולקין מכאן
ומכאן vaneros dalkin mikan u'mikan it might be interesting but we're going
for it. ונרות דולקין מכאן ומכאן vaneros dalkin mikan u'mikan there were
candles both sides of the tunnel until he got to the bathroom.
So we talked about that there was this bathroom which he called
the בית כסא של כבוד beis kisei shel kavod and what was
the כבוד? kavod, That it had a door and that it was
locked. and that you knew that if the door was locked somebody
was there and you didn't go into the space when somebody else
was going to the bathroom. Okay, so let's take a look. The
גמרא now turns to a very much more sort of, you know,
contemporary at least at the time application. רב ספרא הוה יתיב בבית
הכסא, Rav Safra hava yativ b'veit hakeisei, Rav Safra was sitting in
a bathroom
doing his business. אתא רב אבא, Ata Rav Abba, so Rav Abba
comes, נחר ליה, nachar lei, he sort of snorted. Apparently this was
like a signal because according to the גמרא you're not supposed to
talk when you're in the bathroom. So what he did was he
would like snort and then that was like a signal and if
somebody was in the bathroom they were supposed to snort back, you
know, and that would say oh somebody's there and they're not going
to go in. Okay so he did that to see if anybody
was in the bathroom, apparently it didn't have a door, it was
just some space like a hole or something. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so Rav Safra said back, ליעול מר, leieil mar,
come on in. So not only he talked and he was there
and he didn't say stay out, he said come in. So we'll
take a look. So it says so בתר דנפיק, batare d'nafik, so
Rav Abba realized somebody was there and he wasn't going to go
in when somebody was there. So he waited. בתר דנפיק, Batare d'nafik,
so after Rav Safra came out, אמר ליה רב אבא, amar lei
Rav Abba, so Rav Abba said to him, you know, עד כאן
לא סליקת לסעיר וגמרת מילי דסעיר, ad kan lo salikat l'Seir v'gamart
milei d'Seir,
you've never been to Seir and you're acting like a Seirite. Now
it's a little question who does Seir refer to? Does it refer
to Romans? Does it refer to, anyway, clearly it was referring to
some people that they thought were completely, you know, immodest in their
behavior and in their bathroom and in their privacy and all those
types of things. So he says how can you be acting, you've
never been to that place and you're acting like a barbarian, you
know? You go ahead and you told me to come in and
you were in the middle of the bathroom. What is this
nonsense? הכי תנן, Hachi tnan, didn't we teach in our משנה in
תמיד? מצאו נעול בידוע שיש שם אדם, Matzo naul beyadua sheyeish sham
adam, if they found the bathroom locked you know that somebody is
there, which means that our משנה clearly reflects the idea that you're
not supposed to interrupt somebody in a bathroom and it says that
that's כבוד, kavod that that's the proper way of acting. So the
גמרא says למימרא דלא מיבעי ליה למימר, l'meimra d'lo mibaei lei l'meimar,
you're not supposed to go in when somebody else is there. ורב
ספרא סבר, V'Rav Safra savar, so Rav Safra held like Michael said
דילמא מסוכן הוא, dilma mesukan hu, oh no he was afraid, he
was more concerned, you know, he was willing to be מוחל mochel
on his כבוד and he was much more concerned that the guy
had to really had to go and if he wouldn't go there
would be a danger not to go to the bathroom when you
need to.
Which means before he wasn't on just any hole it was just
a space.
No, I assume there was a hole.
A hole in the ground?
Yeah, okay, maybe they were. I don't know. All right I'm just
finishing up. כדתניא, K'datanya, like we taught in a ברייתא, braita: רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, עמוד החוזר מביא
את האדם לידי הדרוקן. amud hachozer meivi et ha'adam lidei hadrokan. If
you have a literally a pillar that goes back, which means that
you are withholding going to the bathroom when you have to go,
it leads to a type of a, you know, of an inflammation
of the stomach, some type of a stomach illness. Hemorrhoids, exactly right?
Yeah, okay, it's about defecating, right? As opposed to סילון החוזר, silon
hachozer, if you have, if you're holding back the stream and you
have to urinate, not defecate, you have to urinate and you're holding
it back, מביא את האדם לידי ירקון, meivi et ha'adam lidei yarkon,
it brings to jaundice. Okay so they were afraid that it would
lead to real illness so that that has to be more important.
So now we're going to have a little couple of stories about
this, a couple of like continuations of this. אמר ליה רב לחייא
בריה, Amar lei Rav l'Chiya breih, so Rav said Chiya's son, וכן
אמר ליה רב הונא לרבה בריה, v'chen amar lei Rav Huna l'Rabbah
breih, and Rav Huna said to Rabbah his son, חשיך תקין נפשך,
chashich takin nafshach, when it gets dark
take care of yourself, meaning go to the bathroom at
nightfall. וקדים תקין נפשך, V'kadim takin nafshach, and get up in the
morning and take care of yourself. Why? Meaning in late, at night
when everybody is sort of at home, so you won't have to,
you can go nearby, you don't have to be afraid other people
are seeing, you don't have to go out in the forest. And
the first thing in the day before people are starting to go
to work also you can go nearby, you don't have to go
out in the forest and so on. Take care of it at
those two times, nobody yet is moving around outside and you don't
have to be embarrassed and you don't have to be afraid about
who else is around and looking and then you won't have to
worry about it for the rest of the day.
Unless everyone's doing that.
That's a good point. Maybe everybody's doing it near their home though,
so whatever. Anyway, I don't know, that's a good point. כי היכי
דלא תרחק, Ki heichi d'lo tirchak, so you don't have to go
way out into the forest. Because if you have to go way
out into the forest, you know, it's dangerous, you don't want to
be going there. And also you might not want to go way
out into the forest and then you'll have these sicknesses. So go
at a time when it's easy, when you won't be embarrassed, when
people aren't around and it's easy to go near the house and
therefore
שלום על ישראל, shalom al Yisrael, you won't have to endanger yourself
by going out into a forest and you won't have to endanger
yourself by not going to the bathroom when you're supposed to go
to the bathroom.
They were still going outside of the house.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. תוב, Tuv, now when you're actually going to the
bathroom, פרוע ושב, pra v'sheiv, first sit and then uncover yourself. Okay,
that's more, you know, modest. Don't expose yourself and then sit. Then
after you're done כסי וקום, kasi v'kum, cover yourself and then stand
up, right? So so you're when you're standing you're always covered. שטוף
ושתי, Shtof u'shetei, rinse out a glass and drink it. שטוף... Shtof...
שטוף shetof ואחית ve'achit and when and rinse it out and then
put it down. So meaning you don't know if the person before
you if they were as fastidious as you were and concerned with
germs and spit. They didn't know about bacteria, but whatever. So rinse
out anything before you use it and also be considerate about the
next person and make sure that maybe the next person won't be
careful but doesn't mean that they should get sick. So rinse it
out after you use it as
well. Okay? Just general cleanliness types of activities. Okay. שפוך
מהן ואחר כך תן לתלמידיך shfoch mehen ve'achar kach ten letalmeidecha and
when you're drinking
water, spill some out and then give to your students. What's that
about? So apparently, what the ראש Rosh says is, is you know,
you would drink and then you would give from the cup you
drank to your students. That would be like, you know, שיריים shirayim
from the רבי, Rebbe, but they might drink from the part your
lips touched and then would have your spit. They didn't know about
germs, but they knew about spit and it would spit on it.
So after you drink, spill out some from where you drank so
that'll clean the lip of the cup and then you can pass
it around to your students and they can drink and they won't
have to ingest.
Meaning everyone else needs to do that too unless they didn't.
I guess so. I guess so. Let's read one more sentence. Okay.
כדתניא ked'tanya like it was taught in a ברייתא: לא ישתה אדם
מים ויתן לתלמידו אלא אם כן שפך מהן, lo yishte adam mayim
veyiten letalmeido ela im ken shafach mehen, don't drink water and give
to your students until you pour out from them first. ומעשה באחד
ששתה מים ולא שפך מהן uma'aseh be'echad sheshata mayim velo shafach mehen
somebody drank water and did not spill out, ונתן לתלמידו venatan letalmeido
and gave to the student, ואותו תלמיד איסטניס היה ve'oto talmid istanis
haya and that תלמיד talmid was a very fastidious person, ולא רצה
לשתות velo ratza lishtot and he refused to drink, and he didn't
drink, ומת בצמא umet batzama and he died of thirst! Which is
a bit like, what? Nobody else had water around? And why couldn't
the תלמיד talmid spill out the water? Maybe that would be disrespectful?
I don't know. באותה שעה אמרו be'ota sha'ah amru at that moment
they said, לא ישתה אדם
מים ויתן לתלמידו אלא אם כן שפך מהן lo yishte adam mayim
veyiten letalmeido ela im ken shafach mehen
don't drink water and give to your student unless you yourself have
poured out from them and one last line: רב אשי אמר, Rav
Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says, הילכך האי תלמידא, hilkach hai
talmida, therefore a certain תלמיד, talmid, דשפיך קמי רביה deshaffich kamey rabbeih
that spills out water in front of his master, לית ביה משום
אפקירותא leit beih mishum apikureita is not considered to be, אפקירותא apikureita
we say is heresy, but the גמרא in סנהדרין Sanhedrin defines it
as disrespect for תורה scholars. So that would not be an act
of disrespect if somebody's spilling water out in front of their רבי
Rebbe because they're doing it because they're trying to clean the cup,
not out of an act of disrespect, and therefore it is something
we don't want him to die of thirst, so something that therefore
we would allow.